Guide to the Maurepas collection, 1694-1749
Maurepas collection, 1694-1749
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Maurepas collection, 1694-1749
4614
Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de Maurepas, 1701-1781.
4.8 linear ft. (694 items)
Manuscripts, administrative documents, correspondence.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Manuscripts, documents, and correspondence from Maurepas's administrative files, documenting his activities as overseer of the country's maritime affairs and of the royal household. Includes letters and documents concerning the War of the Austrian Succession, France's support for the Jacobite cause of Charles Edward, the Young Pretender, in England, and other aspects of French foreign policy; the finances of the French navy; diplomatic relations and commerce with other countries such as Spain, Russia, and Portugal; shipbuilding, navigation, scientific expeditions, and taxation.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Jean-Fréderic Phélypeaux, comte de Maurepas (1701-1781) was a powerful figure in France during the reign of Louis XV, overseeing the administration of both the Royal court and the French Navy during his extended terms as Secretary of the Royal Household (1715-1749) and Secretary of the Navy (1723-1749).
Born into a family of the highest nobility, Maurepas inherited these administrative positions almost as a birthright; they had been held by his grandfather, Louis de Pontchartrain (eventually Chancellier de Pontchartrain), and his father, Jérôme Phélypeaux, comte de Pontchartrain. Maurepas' career began during a "golden age" of French commerce. As Secretary of the Navy, his working philosophy was that the power and security of France depended on the state of its commerce. Accordingly, much of the Navy's activity under Maurepas was aimed at protecting and expanding French foreign and colonial trade. Maurepas' passion for foreign affairs in general, encouraged by his administrative jurisdiction over certain areas of diplomacy and colonial government, led him to overshadow the Foreign Secretary. By the mid 1740s, however, shrinking funds combined with years of war with England had greatly reduced French commerce and the Navy's ability to protect it.
The last ten years of Maurepas' term as Secretary of the Navy were dominated by efforts to manage the escalating English threat to France and her colonies, by the War of Austria Succession (1740-1748), and finally by official war with England (1744). The English threat nudged France into commercial and military co-operation with Spain, at war with England since 1739, and precipitated the involvement of France in the Stuart cause, the Navy planning two ultimately aborted expeditions to Scotland (1743-44) to aid "The Young Pretender". As a member of the Conseil d'en Haut, Maurepas carried his naval experience and agenda to the Aix-la-Chapelle peace negotiations that followed the War of Austrian succession, proposing that any treaty ought to protect France's commercial interests.
Maurepas' ministry promoted improvements in maps, navigation and shipbuilding, and directed expeditions with purely scientific motives to Greece, Peru and the Far East. As Secretary of the Royal Household, Maurepas acted as a patron of the arts, managing the affairs and settling the disputes of the Comédie Française and the Académie Royale. In the latter part of his career, as a minister under Louis XVI, Maurepas remained close to the court. He was responsible for appointing positions in foreign affairs, the royal household and the treasury. Among his nominees was Necker, whom Maurepas dismissed in 1781 for his reformist tendencies.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The Maurepas Collection consists of correspondence, reports, financial and official records, and other papers in French, Spanish and Italian drawn from the administrative files of the comte de Maurepas (1701-1781), Secretary of the Navy and of the Royal Household under Louis XV. The collection consists of 694 items covering the years 1694-1749, with most pertaining to the wartime years 1739-1749. The earliest items predate Maurepas and his ministry, and include a substantial group of letters between Maurepas' father and grandfather, both of whom were government ministers. The Maurepas Papers are divided into two series: letters and documents, with each series arranged chronologically. Letters that accompanied documents have been filed with the correspondence.
As naval minister and liaison to the king, Maurepas served as a clearing-house for a great quantity of often detailed information relayed from all over Europe and the Americas, from land and shipboard, and from men of diverse occupations, rank, and social status. Taken together, the papers document, often through firsthand accounts, the naval, commercial, colonial, and political history of France in the first half of the eighteenth century. Much of the incoming correspondence is concerned with ways to increase the strength and improve the operations of the Navy in a period of intense commercial and military competition with Britain, and with sounding out foreign territories and governments for possible acquisition or economic exploitation by France.
Major subjects include war with England; the War of Austrian Succession; France's support of the Jacobite cause in England, and other aspects of French foreign policy; the state and position of the French, British and Spanish navies; colonial expeditions to Louisiana and Canada; Navy finances; taxation; diplomatic relations and exterior trade with Spain, Portugal, Russia, the Levant, and others; colonial trade; South American expeditions; armaments; shipbuilding; navigation; cartography and hydrography; scientific expeditions; life at the court of Versailles; and the royal academies of the arts.
Documents include reports and memoranda on the military, navigational and engineering problems encountered by the French Navy; proposals for reform and innovation (marine law, methods of recruitment, fundraising); plans for inventions, such as a dredging machine; military and other campaign orders; illustrated instruction booklets on sailing and navigation; journals; royal ordonnances, some printed; inventories of ships, arms and provisions; personnel records; financial records; a letter of marque authorizing a privateer; and assorted requests for promotions, raises, and titles.
As Secretary of the Royal Household, Maurepas corresponded with members of the Comédie Française and Académie Royale de Musique, mostly concerning disputes between performers and directors. Personal papers include letters from Maurepas' aunt informing him of life and court politics at Versailles, and correspondence with his aristocratic friends.
Principal correspondents include Jérôme Phélypeaux, comte de Pontchartrain; Louis de Pontchartrain (Chancelier); his aunt Armande de la Porte Mazarin, marquise de Mailly-Nesle; Joseph Pellerin, First Clerk of the Navy; Voltaire; Louis XV; Charles Edward Stuart ("The Young Pretender"); King George II; Thomond; Louis François Armand, duc de Richelieu; Nicolas de la Rochefoucauld, duc d'Enville; Saint-Simon.
Jean V. Callahan
11 December 1995
The guide to the Maurepas collection was produced with funding provided by the United States Department of Education grant Title II-C, "Strengthening Research Library Resources": The French Revolution Collections at Cornell University: a Retrospective Conversion and Preservation Project.
Project staff included Jean V. Callahan, Peggy John, and Isabel Rivera. The Maurepas website (guide and exhibit) was conceived by Jean V. Callahan and implemented by Noni Korf Vidal.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux,--comte de,--1701-1781.; Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux,--comte de,--1701-1781.; Pontchartrain, Jérome Phélypeaux,--comte de,--1674-1747.; Pontchartrain, Louis,--comte de.; Pontchartrain, Jérome Phélypeaux,--comte de,--1674-1747.; Pontchartrain, Louis,--comte de.; Mailly-Nesle, Armande de la Porte Mazarin,--marquise de.; Charles Edward,--Prince, grandson of James II, King of England,--1720-1788.; Richelieu, Louis François Armand Du Plessis,--duc de,--1696-1788.; Louis XV,--King of France,--1710-1774.; Pellerin, Joseph.; Voltaire,--1694-1778.--Précis du siècle de Louis XV.; Saint-Simon, Louis de Rouvroy,--duc de,--1675-1755.; France.--Marine.; Comédie Française.; France.--Ministère de la marine.; France.--Ministère de la maison du roi.
Subjects:
Finance, Public--France.; Shipbuilding--France.; Cartography--France.; Navigation--France.
Places:
France--History--Louis XV, 1715-1774--Sources.; France--History--Regency, 1715-1723--Sources.; France--History, Naval--18th century--Sources.; France--Politics and government--1715-1774.; France--Foreign relations--1715-1774.; France--Economic policy.; France--Economic conditions--18th century.; France--Commerce-- Spain--History.; France--Commerce-- Soviet Union--History.; France--Commerce-- Portugal--History.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
HISTORY OF OWNERSHIP
Cornell's Maurepas Collection is based upon a large and important segment of the ministerial papers of Jean Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de Maurepas et de Pontchartain (1701-1781). Until 1962 these papers had been maintained largely intact but in private hands. In that year they were dispersed, with the bulk of the Secretary's general correspondence and the materials related to the King's Household going to the Archives Nationales in Paris. The extremely important naval papers were, however, held back and auctioned at Parke-Bernet Galleries of New York on March 6 of the same year.
PROVENANCE
Through the generosity of Arthur H. and Mary Marden Dean, Cornell was able to take advantage of a unique opportunity and acquire the bulk of this naval archive -- a total of 652 items, including most of the important lots and individual pieces. In 1968 the Deans added to the collection a second block of material consisting of 42 pieces of family correspondence not included in the 1962 sale.
BOX DESCRIPTIONS
- Box One
  Correspondence from 1694-1709; undated incoming correspondence.
  Includes correspondence of Maurepas' father, mother and grandfather, the majority of which are letters from Jérome Phélypeaux, Maurepas' father, reporting as Secretary of the Navy to Maurepas' grandfather, the Chancellier de Pontchartrain, from various port cities in France. Also from this early period: a series of reports to the Chancellier from Bory and Chabert concerning the expedition of the Aimable to South America (including a ten page description of the Brazilian coast), and a letter from Bigorre to Cardinal Fleury.
  Correspondence dating from Maurepas' ministry concerns war with England, the Bastille and colonizing Patagonia. Of particular interest is a note from Voltaire in his capacity as royal historiographer requesting information for his history of the Navy.
- Box Two
  Correspondence from 1707-1709 and 1732-1741.
  Includes seven more letters from Bory and Chabert to the Chancellier de Pontchartrain concerning the South American expedition.
  Correspondence dating from Maurepas' ministry consists primarily of reports and memoranda related to foreign trade and Franco-British hostilities. There are also journal extracts, recommendations, and requests for raises, promotions and appointments.
  Topics addressed include: the possible acquisition of l'Isle de Tabarque; trade with Turkey and the Levant; information on the Turkish government and consulates in Turkey and Egypt; gunner ships; English seizure of French ships; the "new" Spanish Navy*; movement of French and foreign ships in the Caribbean; commerce in Marseilles; commercial navigation; solution to recruitment problems (complaints about an ordonnance of 1734); British free navigation in the West Indies*; poor living conditions aboard ship; a sea-battle off Santo Domingo; a solution to malfunctioning ship engine*.
  There are letters from Maurepas to d'Antin, to d'Enville, and one to Champigny on fortifications at St. Lucie and the capture of the Barbadoes.
  Of special interest: Duclerq's 1741 journal of events in Jamaica, with commentary on a sea-battle with the English; a series of letters from Maurepas to d'Antin giving him information about the British and instructions in case of a war; a fifty-page report on the commerce of Marseilles with the Levant; a letter in code from Larnage to Orry, the Comptroller General.
  * These letters have accompanying documents filed in Boxes 8 - 15.
- Box Three
  Correspondence from May 1741-1744.
  Correspondence from this period reflects continuing Franco-British hostilities at sea (which culminated in a declaration of war in March 1744), the French Navy's involvement in the Jacobite cause, continuing efforts to expand foreign commerce, and the more mundane internal affairs of the Navy. Several letters deal with family and court matters. There are a number of letters from the duc d'Enville and comte de Luzerne, as well as letters accompanying documents and requests for promotions, raises, recommendations, etc.
  Topics addressed include: English invasion in defense of the Stuart cause; commercial treaties with Prussia and Portugal; naval provisions supply; armament projects*; treasure*; recruitment*; royal fireworks; the Bastille.
  Of special interest: Pellerin's plan for the invasion of England; Four letters from Meilly-Nesle, Maurepas' aunt and an influential member of the court; letters from Irish Jacobite, O'Bryen, appealing to Maurepas for aid in the Jacobite Revolution; a letter from the marquise de Mézières, daughter of a Court officer to James II and an Irish mother, married to a Frenchman, describing her role as agent of Protestant Jacobite faction; a letter in Spanish from Campo-Florida to Spanish Secretary of State Muniain that discusses French plan for attacking British ships.
- Box Four
  Correspondence from 1745-October 24, 1745.
  During this period, France was officially at war with England, a second attempt at invading Britain was being planned, and the Navy was seriously underfunded. Louisbourg fell to the English. There are many letters from Pellerin, First Clerk of the Navy, and several pertaining to Maurepas' duties as Secretary of the Royal Household.
  Topics addressed include: the Jacobite cause; French maritime commerce; raising funds for the Navy*; war booty; life at the Royal Court; requests for promotions; Opéra disputes.
  Of special interest: A letter from James III requesting French aid for the "Young Pretender" of Scotland; letters from Irish Jacobites O'Bryen and O'Heguarty, with suggestions for French intervention in Stuart cause; a report by the shipowner Fournier about the serious state of maritime commerce and how to rehabilitate the Navy.
- Box Five
  Correspondence from October 25, 1745 - January 17, 1746.
  The correspondence from this period tracks the preparation of a second expedition to Britain, and an expedition under the duc d'Enville to recapture Louisbourg (which failed). The Navy's financial crisis continues. A major focus on the domestic front is the separation agreement of the Prince and Princesse de Talmond; Maurepas represented the Princesse, who was a frequent correspondent during this period. There are many letters to Maurepas from Thomond and Saint-Simon.
  Topics addressed include: preparations for the British expedition; separation agreement of the de Talmonds; life at the court of Louis XV; Opéra disputes; requests for favors.
  Of special interest: Letters from Thomond, Maurepas' friend and intermediary in France's involvement in Jacobite cause; A letter from the Duke of York delivered to Maurepas via the Irish Jacobite O'Bryen; letters from Irish Jacobites Walsh and O'Bryen involved in the expedition; a letter from Richelieu as commander-in-chief of the expedition.
- Box Six
  Correspondence from January 1746 - December 1746.
  This year saw the defeat of the Jacobites and the failure of the American expedition to recapture Louisbourg. There are many letters from Maurepas' friend, the earl of Thomond.
  Topics include: movements of ships; the American expedition; raising funds for the "Young Pretender"; the defeat of the Jacobites; French and Spanish corsair warfare; Franco-Spanish relations; various requests.
  Of special interest: orders from Louis XV to the duc d'Enville regarding the American expedition to recapture Louisbourg; letters from Thomond, Maurepas' friend and the intermediary in France's involvement with the Jacobite cause; a letter from the marquise de Mézières reporting Jacobite defeat; a letter describing Charles Stuart's departure from Scotland; a letter from the Duke of York; firsthand account by Ambassador Chavigny of diplomatic relations with Spain; a letter from Estourmel (suicide), asking relief from command of "Le Trident" because of low numbers and an extract from the journal of Montlouet, officer on "Le Trident," recounting Estourmel's mental degeneration.
- Box Seven
  Correspondence from December 10, 1746 - December 29, 1747.
  In this year the French were defeated in battles at Capes Finisterre and Ortegal.
  Topics include: Navy archives; Marseilles; duc d'Enville's death; manoeuvers of British ships; plans of the Spanish court; the Corsican situation; the campaign against the Austrians (besieging Genoa); suggestions about trade policy; a commercial treaty with Spain; comments on the Belle l'Isle campaign; the Talmond separation agreement; various appeals and requests.
  Of special interest: letters from Laffilard, chief of Navy archives, which contain information about the archives and cataloguing procedures; firsthand account by Ambassador Chavigny of diplomatic relations with Spain; a letter from Thomond recounting his career; a letter from Duval, ship surgeon on the "Northumberland," describing d'Enville's illness and death; two letters from Charles Edward Stuart announcing his arrival in France via Spain.
- Box Eight
  Documents: undated and from 1707-1732.
  Documents include: many papers associated with the expedition of the Aimable to South America (remarks on the Brazilian coast, commerce in New Spain, the "decadence" of Chile and Peru); a fifteen-page description of Louisiana by D'Artaguiette; a series of substantial memoranda by d'Aubenton on Spanish ports and French trade in Catalonia, Grenada and other Spanish colonies; a printed account of sea combat with English; Macary's invention (dredging machine); a list of ships; a record of sums paid to retiring officers; petitions and requests; a letter of introduction; labelled folders (empty) from Maurepas' files.
  Other reports and memoranda address: the present state of the Navy; the Navy's expenses for 1732; armaments; ship construction; combat; the children of dead officers.
- Box Nine
  Documents from 1732-1739.
  Several long reports from Maillet on activities in Mediterranean; observations on a problem in ship structure and a fifty-three page booklet detailing a solution; memoranda on map correction; a twenty page letter on the Spanish Navy; several reports on the abuse of French flags; a proposal by Maurepas for intervention in Corsica; commentary on a Royal ordonnance of 1734; a royal decree concerning Genoa; lists of officers.
  Other reports and memoranda address: English methods of naval construction; the use of flags by the French Navy; Spanish silk trade; commerce with Russia; armaments; Turkish government; consulates in the Levant; goods and supplies; treasure; Isle de Tabarque; Navy finances; expenses in colonies.
- Box Ten
  Documents from 1739-1740.
  Many documents pertain to the hostile relationship between France and England, largely acted out at sea and in the colonies. There is a considerable number of items from Barry, the Commissaire des Classes at Marseilles.
  Documents directly related to war with England cover: the arming of English ships; how to defend coasts of France from English threat; English presence in America; English request for free navigation; naval orders. There are two British documents concerning corsair warfare with Spain.
  Other documents include: instructions to officers from Maurepas; notes on galley construction; an instruction booklet on methods of sailing (with color diagrams); reports on maritime laws, navigation, movement of ships, armament and the arsenal, the crew of the Reales, ship names, pensions, the Bureau des Classes; a list of offences punishable by galleys; various requests.
  Notable documents include: a twenty-one page journal kept by the French Jesuit, Vitry, on an expedition against Native Americans in Louisiana (contains a detailed account of Indian life); a significant study of French trade and its political function by Buthaud (a good articulation of the philosophy behind Maurepas' administrative policy); a study of French trade; printed rules for corsair warfare decreed by George III of England; a description of an invention; a description of the civil and military functions of Admiral; an illustrated booklet on maritime manoeuvres.
- Box Eleven
  Documents from January 11, 1740 to May 1741.
  There are many documents written by Pellerin. Also: a draft of a trade treaty with Portugal; a proposal for replenishing Navy funds through taxation; a new plan for the Navy (with observations on the British Navy); a draft by Maurepas establishing the current primary concerns of the Navy; documents relating to d'Antin's illness and estate and to the Gigou affair; instructions for officers; a resume of d'Antin's campaign in the West Indies; promotion orders; lists of ships.
  Reports and memoranda also address: British maritime activities; the British threat to possessions in America; armaments; expenses; supply of provisions; fate of provisions in shipwrecks; lodgings; war casualties; the need for instructions for officiers de plumes; payments to veterans.
  Of special interest: a memorandum on reforming maritime laws, including a history of the law and a series of questions and answers about specific articles.
- Box Twelve
  Documents from May 27, 1741 - March 1743.
  Reports and memoranda concerning: the fireworks display for King's birthday; armament expenses for 1740-42; improving the status of navigators; income from tenth of seizures; anchorage fees; recruitment problems and plans for improvement; the Mediterranean squadron; the security of Santo Domingo; threat of war with England; plan for trade treaty with Prussia.
  Other documents include: an inventory of French and foreign ships; campaign orders from Louis XV.
  Of special interest: a twenty-two page report on the degeneration of the French Navy and proposals for its improvement (discusses disciplinary problems and is implicitly critical of Maurepas' ministry, rather than simply blaming the lack of funds); a memorandum by Pellerin on the preparedness of the Navy in the event of war with England; a proposal by Cossigny to establish a port of call on Ascension Island, with a description of the Island and plans for water supply, etc.; report by Duvalaer and Robion on the finances of a proposed expedition to South America.
- Box Thirteen
  Documents from April 1743 - c. 1744.
  Reports and memoranda concerning: the wealth of France; ship construction; Navy expenses and funds; taxation; provisions; expanding French trade and navigation; Spanish trade and French trade with Spain; the West Indies; "prises juger"; proposed expedition to Pacific coast of South America; commerce of Venice and Livorne with Egypt; Genoa's position during Anglo-Spanish war; problems with British in Spanish America.
  Other documents include: lists of officers; descriptions of ships; a royal edict.